Ralph Izard Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ralph Izard Family Papers 1778-1826 (bulk 1801-1814)
MSS27524
Izard, Ralph, 1742-1804
660 items
5 containers plus 1 oversize
2.0 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Continental congressman, United States senator from South Carolina, diplomat. Correspondence and miscellaneous material concerning the Izard family regarding domestic life and social affairs in Charleston, South Carolina, and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and including the involvement of family members in managing their estate in South Carolina and the Tripolitan War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Izard family.; Izard, Alice DeLancey, 1745-1832--Correspondence.; Izard, Elizabeth Middleton, 1787-1822--Correspondence.; Izard, George, 1777-1828.; Izard, Ralph, 1742-1804.; Izard, Ralph, 1785-1824--Correspondence.; Manigault, Margaret Izard, 1768-1824--Correspondence.; Parker, John, 1759-1832--Correspondence.; Pinckney, Thomas, 1750-1828--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Navy--History--Tripolitan War, 1801-1805.
Places
Charleston (S.C.)--Social life and customs.; Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Social life and customs.; South Carolina--Social life and customs.; United States--History--Tripolitan War, 1801-1805.
Occupations
Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--South Carolina.; Diplomats.; Senators, U.S. Congress--South Carolina.
Provenance
The papers of the Ralph Izard family were purchased, 1910-1958.
Additional Guides
The Ralph Izard Family Papers are described in Report of the Librarian of Congress for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1930. (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1930), p. 72.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Ralph Izard family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on two reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1742, Jan. 23 Born near Charleston, S.C.
1767 Married Alice DeLancy (died 1832)
1771 1776 Resided in London, England, and Paris, France
1776 1779 Served as commissioner to the Court of Tuscany for the Continental Congress
1780 Pledged his estate in South Carolina for the payment of warships to be used in the American Revolution
1782 1783 Member, Continental Congress
1789 1796 Served in United States Senate; president pro tempore of the senate
1804, May 30 Died, near Charleston, S.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Ralph Izard Family Papers span the years 1778-1826, with the bulk of the material dating from 1801-1814. The correspondence includes letters of Ralph Izard (1742-1804) relating to his Charleston, South Carolina, estate and the education of his son George Izard (1777-1828); letters of his son, Ralph Izard (1785-1824), relating in part to his service with the United States Navy during the Tripolitan War; and the letters of Alice DeLancey Izard (1745-1832), Margaret Izard Manigault (1768-1824), and Elizabeth Middleton Izard (1787-1822) relating to family and domestic life and to social affairs in Charleston, South Carolina, and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Other correspondents include Thomas Pinckney and John Parker.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged chronologically by year with an alphabetical listing by name of person thereunder. Fragments and miscellaneous material are filed at the end.
Container List
- 1778-1805, (7 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Burrows, W. W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Gadsden, Christopher (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Izard, Alice DeLancey (Mrs. Ralph) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Izard, Ralph (1742-1804) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Izard, Ralph (1785-1824) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Manigault, Harriet (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Manigault, Margaret Izard (Mrs. Gabriel) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Parker, John (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Pinckney, Thomas (Box 1, Reel 1)
- 1806-1810, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Izard, Elizabeth Middleton (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Izard, Ralph (1785-1824) (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Manigault, Charlotte (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Manigault, Margaret Izard (Box 2, Reel 1)
- 1811-1814, Mar., (6 folders) (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Deas, Ann Izard (Mrs. William Allen) (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Izard, Alice DeLancey (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Izard, Ann Middleton (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Izard, Elizabeth Middleton (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Izard, Ralph (1785-1824) (Box 3, Reel 1-2)
  - Manigault, Margaret Izard (Box 3, Reel 1)
- 1814 Apr.-1823, (6 folders) (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Alice DeLancey (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ann Middleton (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Elizabeth Middleton (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ralph (1785-1824) (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Manigault, Margaret Izard (Box 4, Reel 2)
- 1824-1826, (3 folders) (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Adela (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ann Middleton (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Eliza Lucas Pinckney (Mrs. Ralph, Jr.) (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Margaret (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ralph (Box 5, Reel 2)
- Undated (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Alice DeLancey (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ann Middleton (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Izard, Ralph (1785-1824) (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - Manigault, Margaret Izard (Box 5, Reel 2)
- Fragments (Box 5, Reel 2)
- Miscellaneous (Box 5, Reel 2)